Finding Aid for Dept. of Speech (University of Michigan) records, 1928-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Speech (University of Michigan) records 1928-1978
University of Michigan. Department of Speech.
87159 Bimu F41 2
Scrapbooks, 1928-1972, of programs, publicity, and newspaper clippings compiled by the directors and staff of various University theatrical productions; history of University play production, 1909-1956; and departmental correspondence and miscellanea.
31 linear feet
6 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Speech records have come from three sources. The department itself gave records in 1955 (donor no. 3168 ). Between 1956 and 1966, William P. Halstead (donor no. 3190 ), both personally and as executor of the Valentine Windt estate, gave the bulk of the records. Most recently, members of the Theatre and Drama Department have donated files regarding their predecessor unit (donor no. 7234 ).
The records are open for use without restriction.
Michigan was among the first schools in the nation to formally incorporate instruction in the field of speech into its curriculum. The subject's inclusion was largely the result of Thomas C. Trueblood's work. In the later nineteenth century, Trueblood made his living traveling from university to university offering short courses in speech. He first came to Ann Arbor in 1884 and his six week course was so popular with students that he began to return for longer and longer residences. Finally, in 1889 he became a permanent faculty member of the University of Michigan. In 1892 the Department of Elocution and Oratory was created, with Trueblood as its sole member. Trueblood remained chair of the department until 1926.
Over the years the department's formal title changed frequently, reflecting the broad area of instruction that fell under its mantle. The original name was simplified to the Department of Oratory in 1908. Subsequent titles included Department of Public Speaking (1919-1927); Department of Speech (1927-1932); Department of Speech, Phonetics, and General Linguistics (1932); Department of Speech and General Linguistics (1932-1939); Department of Speech (1939-1972); and Department of Speech Communication and Theater (1972-1979). In 1979, as part of a major reorganization of several units, the Department of Speech Communication and Theater was formally eliminated. Elements of the department's program were relocated in two new units; the Department of Theatre and Drama and the Department of Communication.
Records of the Department of Speech include 31 linear feet of material and 6 oversize scrapbooks, dating from 1928 to 1982. Virtually all of the records relate directly to the department's work in theater education. Included are extensive records of university theatrical productions (1938-1972); records of the University Players, a student organization dedicated to presenting live theater on campus; and general information regarding theater in Ann Arbor. Actual department records make up a small minority of the documentation found within the collection, although some information regarding a 1972 unit review and the decisions leading to the 1979 reorganization of the department are included. Photographs include images of plays and actors in various University theatrical productions.
Subjects:
Drama.; Theater--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University Players (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Dramatics.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Theatrical productions.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Speech.; University of Michigan--Dramatics.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Programs of play productions
  - 1928-1938 (Box 1)
  - 1938-1948 (Box 1)
  - 1948-1958 (Box 1)
  - 1958-1963 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1968 (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks concerning play productions and speech department affairs
  - 1928-1949 (Box 2)
  - 1950-1955 (Box 3)
  - 1955-1959 (Box 4)
  - 1959-1960 (Box 5)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 6)
  - 1962-1963 (Box 7)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 8)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 9)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 10)
  - 1967-1968 (Box 12)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 13)
  - 1969-1970 (Box 14)
  - 1970-1972 (Box 15)
- Miscellanea
  - Play productions miscellanea (Box 11)
- Historical files
  - "History of Plays at the University of Michigan, 1909-1956" (Box 16)
  - Early play production materials (Box 16)
  - Power Center Committee financial records (Box 16)
  - Studio Lab Theater
    - Lab Bill Information (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous Documents 1962-1982, 4 folders (Box 16)
  - University Players 50th Anniversary brochure (Box 16)
- Photograph albums of play productions
  - 1928-1941 (Box 17)
  - 1941-1951 (Box 18)
  - 1952-1957 (Box 19)
  - 1958-1961 (Box 20)
  - 1962-1965 (Box 21)
  - 1966-1971 (Box 22)
- Notebooks and Miscellaneous
  - Speech Department Graduate Committee 1967-1970 (Box 23)
    (notebooks of minutes of meetings)
  - University Players notebooks:
    - Minutes of committee meetings (Box 23)
    - Audits (Box 23)
    - Publicity and promotions (Box 23)
    - Press and correspondence of Richard Lutz (Box 23)
  - Speech department notebooks (Box 24)
  - University Players notebooks (Box 24)
  - Non-speech department notebooks (Box 24)
  - Speech department notebooks (Box 25)
  - University Players notebooks (Box 25)
  - Non-speech department notebooks (Box 25)
  - Professional Theatre Program notebooks (Box 25)
  - Notebooks containing clippings and notices of theatre in Ann Arbor: (Box 26)
    - Professional Theatre Program 1971-1974, 2 volumes (Box 26)
    - Ann Arbor Restaurant Theatre (Box 26)
    - Miscellaneous: Gilbert and Sullivan, MUSKET, etc. (Box 26)
  - Notebooks containing clippings and notices of theatre in Ann Arbor (cont.) (Box 26)
    - Miscellaneous: Washtenaw County productions, etc. (Box 26)
    - Miscellaneous: Rock and jazz presentations (Box 26)
  - Programs of play productions 1968-1973 (Box 26)
  - Professional Theatre Program notebook 1968-1969 (Box 26)
  - Notebook containing drafts of memos and notes of W. P. Halstead concerning G. E. Densmore and speech department affairs, 2 volumes (Box 26)
  - Notebooks containing correspondence of W. P. Halstead with Robert Schnitzer and Ellis Rabb, 2 volumes (Box 26)
  - Notebooks containing clippings regarding theatre in Ann Arbor, including:, 19 volumes (Box 27)
    - Competitive Theatre (Box 27)
    - Professional Theatre Program (Box 27)
    - University Players (Box 27)
    - Theatre Committee (Box 27)
  - Papers concerning thesis on the Professional Theatre Program written by Robert Chapel, and criticism of the thesis by Robert C. Schnitzer (Box 27)
- Department of Speech
  - History of the department 1942, 1973 (Box 28)
  - Guide to the Study of Film at the University of Michigan 1973 (Box 28)
  - Honors convocation (speech) 1941-1957 (Box 28)
  - Minutes 1962-1964 (Box 28)
  - Organization and instruction undated (Box 28)
  - Theatre area
    - Activity 1960-1964 (Box 28)
    - Assistantships and fellowships 1965-1973 (Box 28)
    - Black theatre 1971-1976 (Box 28)
    - Doctor of Arts degree proposal 1972 (Box 28)
    - Halstead, William (obituary) (Box 28)
    - International Festival of Experimental Theatre 1975 (Box 28)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 28)
    - Policies circa 1966-1970 (Box 28)
    - Power Center 1964, 1968-1971 (Box 28)
    - Review of Theatre Area 1972-1974 (Box 28)
    - Separation Committee 1978 (Box 28)
    - Theatre Committee minutes 1975-1980 (Box 28)
  - Windt, Valentine B. 1936 (Box 28)
- University Players
  - Awards and membership lists 1968-1971 (Box 28)
  - Children's Theatre (Box 28)
  - Christmas Plays 1965-1972 (Box 28)
  - General 1962-1971, 2 folders (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous Documents 1962-1973 (Box 28)
- Photographs
  - Pictures of productions 1935-1950 (Box 29)
  - Portraits of actors (Box 29)
  - Abbey Theatre Company (portraits of Valentine Windt) (Box 29)
- Scrapbooks regarding play productions
  - 1938-1939 (Volume 1)
  - 1942-1948 (Volume 2)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 30)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 30)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 30)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 30)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 30)
  - Summer 1944 (Box 30)
  - Summer 1945 (Volume 3)
  - Summer 1946 (Volume 4)
  - Summer 1947 (Volume 5)
  - Summer 1948 (Volume 6)
  - Summer 1949 (Box 31)
  - Summer 1950 (Box 31)
  - Summer 1951 (Box 31)
  - Summer 1953 (Box 31)
  - Summer 1954 (Box 31)
  - Summer 1955 (Box 31)
  - Summer 1956 (Box 31)
  - Summer 1957 (Box 31)